<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The voice of truth, uttered forth against the unreasonablenes, rudenes, and deboistnes of the rulers, teachers and people of the island Barbados. Through one, who hath suffered by them, for the testimony of a good conscience, and the word of God, known by the name of Thomas Clark.</title>
            <author>Clark, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 24 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79907</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4562A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171379</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789243</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789243</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172553</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79907)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172553)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2638:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The voice of truth, uttered forth against the unreasonablenes, rudenes, and deboistnes of the rulers, teachers and people of the island Barbados. Through one, who hath suffered by them, for the testimony of a good conscience, and the word of God, known by the name of Thomas Clark.</title>
                  <author>Clark, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Robert Wilson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  Persecutions --  Barbados --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172553:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VOICE OF TRUTH, Uttered forth againſt the UNREASONABLENES, RUDENES, and DEBOISTNES of the RULERS, TEACHERS and PEOPLE of the <hi>Iſland</hi> BARBADOS.</p>
            <p>Through one, who hath ſuffered by them, for the Teſtimony of a Good Conſcience, and the Word of God; known by the Name of <hi>THOMAS CLARK.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:172553:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:172553:2"/>
            <head>The Voice of Truth uttered forth againſt the Unreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Rudeneſs, and Deboiſtneſs of the Rulers, Teachers and People of the Iſland <hi>BARBADOS.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>OH ye Rulers, and Magiſtrates, who are now in Authoritie; how do you ſlight the Goodneſs of God, in this the day of your Viſitation, inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as you have cauſed the Innocent to ſuffer, and let the guilty go free? Oh Friends, how doth wickedneſs abound, in Townes and Countrey, and alſo in your own Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, (where firſt it ought to be puniſhed) as alſo in your own Particulars? in ſo doing you would become good Examples in your own Families, and alſo general Patterns of good through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Land: ſo would you be a Terrour to the Wicked, and Evil Doers; and a Praiſe to them that do Well: and herein would you anſwer the Righteous Law of God, written in the heart; which is according to the Apoſtles Doctrine: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of that, which bringeth into the Moderation in your own Particulars, ye cannot with ſafety puniſh others for the things whereof you are Guilty; and ſo living in the Exceſſe your ſelves, others eyes are upon you, and take example by you, to do as you do, and to follow after the fame exceſſe of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs; and ſuch are accepted of you, and countenanced by you, whereby the wicked are become very ſtrong; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that they run into wickedneſs with greedineſs, and commit Lewdneſs as with Zeal; and ſo Mercy, and true Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is forſaken in the Land, and the Righteous Law of God (which is to do unto all men as you would they ſhould do unto you) is turned backward; and Righteouſneſs, and Equitie, is counted a Ridiculous thing; and the Holy Spirit of God, which teacheth the Law of the Lord, &amp; leadeth into all Truth, this is made a mock of, and is had in Deriſion dayly through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Land; and the Blood of the Everlaſting Covenant of God is trampled upon, and accounted of as an horrible thing; and thus it is come to paſſe; and thus you ſuffer to be done
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172553:3"/>unto them who keep in Gods Holy Covenant, and obey the Holy Spirit of God; and do Meditate on his Righteous Law Day and Night, by which they are led, and guided up to God; and in all things to do as they would be done unto, and for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring this in Doctrine, Life, &amp; Converſation; and for bearing our Teſtimonies againſt falſe Prophets, &amp; againſt falſe Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſuch as Preach for Hire, and will be drunk in Tavernes, and other places; <hi>Who are Covetous, Proud, Boaſters, Heady, High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded, Lovers of Pleaſures, more then Lovers of God,</hi> &amp;c. Tim. 3. Such as the Apoſtle ſpoke of, and bore his Teſtimony againſt: and for our declaring againſt them, and ſuch as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them in thoſe things; who are become one with them; like Prieſt like People, all in the Errour, out of the Fear of the Lord; committing all manner of Lewdneſs, and runing dayly into all manner of exceſſe of wickedneſs, with greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: In conſideration whereof, many is the time that my Life hath been heavily burthened, and my Soul grieved; which hath cauſed me to walk Sorrowfully, day after day, to ſee how greedily the People run on to their Everlaſting De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, &amp; fat up themſelves in wickedneſs, as the Ox for the ſlaughter: Oh! ye <hi>Rulers,</hi> when I have conſidered how theſe People are ſtrengthened by you, thus to run on in <hi>Lewdneſs</hi> and <hi>all manner of Prophanneſs,</hi> againſt the <hi>Righteous God that made them,</hi> then hath my heart been grieved for you, and have hazarded my Life for you, and for them; and have freely given up my Life for your ſakes, being thereunto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of the <hi>Lord,</hi> whoſe Tender Viſitation hath been over you; by whom I have been ſent amongſt you, at your <hi>Meetings</hi> to acquaint you that it was the <hi>Day of Gods Love,</hi> and <hi>Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> towards you, and to declare againſt your <hi>ungodly Worſhip, Lives</hi> and <hi>Practices,</hi> to the end you might hearken thereunto, and that you might be turned from the <hi>Darkneſs</hi> to the <hi>Light,</hi> and from <hi>Satans Power,</hi> unto the <hi>Power of the Living God,</hi> which is the ſame the Apoſtles Preached, and brought People into: for which Doctrine they ſuffered grievouſly, by the Men of that Generation; even as I have done by the hands of this Generation, for bearing the ſame Teſtimony as they did, namely, my Wife <hi>haled out of her houſe,</hi> by <hi>Samuel Graves</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:172553:3"/>Prieſt, who alſo tore off ſome of her Clothes, in the <hi>open Street,</hi> in ſight of many People, by which my Children that were crying about her, were affrighted, and received hurt thereby, and my People <hi>beaten</hi> from their work and <hi>haled</hi> by the <hi>hair</hi> of the <hi>head,</hi> and threatned with grievous Language, what he would do unto them: this was done by the ſaid <hi>Graves,</hi> and his Wife, and my ſelf abuſed very much at ſeveral times, for Truths ſake; once haled to the Stocks and there ſet till the Prieſt had done; and after committed to Priſon: once for coming to their Meeting at <hi>Speights Town,</hi> to ſhew the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates that were there, how the Prieſts People were beating and abuſing ſome of my Friends, with <hi>ſore Kicks,</hi> and <hi>heavy Blowes,</hi> with <hi>Staves,</hi> and <hi>Cudgels;</hi> which thing was ſuffered to be done in ſight of the Magiſtrates, and the People that did it were ſtrengthened by them; and for declaring unto them my Friends Sufferings, how they were abuſed, that they might ſtill the People, by whoſe Wickedneſs my Friends lives lay in danger. In anſwer thereunto, Command was given <hi>to take me away,</hi> the which was done by wicked People, who ſorely beat me with great Cudgels, and Staves, with ſore Kicks on my Belly, and other parts of my Body; and ſo they carryed me to the <hi>Stocks,</hi> with my hands and feet with the ſmall of my back croſs a Cudgel, ſhaking and abuſing me in that manner unto the <hi>Stocks,</hi> as a ſheep carrying to the Butcher; and after, with my Friends, committed to Priſon. Another time; for put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up a Friends Paper, at the Pariſh houſe, called <hi>Lucies Church;</hi> in which Paper was declared againſt <hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> and <hi>all manner of Wickedneſs,</hi> exhorting People to <hi>turn therefrom,</hi> and <hi>repent thereof;</hi> for which thing I was taken into the houſe, by one of their Church Officers, called <hi>Miles Scotto,</hi> who ſaid I ſhould receive no wrong, with whom I went in, where Prieſt <hi>Gray</hi> and his People were met together, and ſpake theſe words to the People; <hi>I came in at the requeſt of the ſaid Scotto, who Promiſed I ſhould receive no wrong,</hi> but before I had fully uttered theſe words, my Hat was pulled off, and by the People I was haled to the door, and thrown down three or four ſteps; and I getting up, they fell upon me, and beat me with Cudgels, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till I fell down as dead: and as I lay in that manner, ſeveral
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172553:4"/>ſtood beating me with their Staves, as I was told, after I was recovered; and when my ſences were come unto me, it was laid upon me to ſpeak to the People in Love, to ſhew them <hi>the Evil they had done,</hi> and deſired <hi>that the Lord might not lay it to their charge;</hi> for which ſeveral of them fell upon me again, and <hi>beat me,</hi> and <hi>punched me with their Sticks very much,</hi> and ſo continued following of me for a good ſpace on my way. This was alſo done in the ſight of <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> and ſeveral others <hi>Officers</hi> that were there, who had Power to have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented it, but did not, but rather ſtrengthened the People, I pray God it be not laid to their charge. Alſo by <hi>Matthew Gray</hi> Prieſt of the ſame Pariſh, ſometimes after, upon the Day the King was Proclaimed, came Drunk to a Tavern over againſt my houſe, and I looking out at my Chamber-window, he ſeeing me, called to me, and held up his Horſe Whip, ſhaking at me; and ſaid, <hi>Tom, you muſt come no more to my Church, for now</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>we have got a King;</hi> and ſo ſet Boys, and other Rude People to ſtone me in at my Window, and alſo ſeveral Perſons with their Guns, who ſhot at me, by which I received ſome injury, at which he rejoyced, and leaped, and skipped about the Roome, and further endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in my hearing (what he could) to get the People to pull down my houſe; and more, I was informed, that he bid ſome to fire my houſe; but before he came the People were quiet, and offered me no wrong.</p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Thomas Manwaring</hi> Prieſt at <hi>Speights Town,</hi> came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe of <hi>Anthony Long,</hi> where I was about ſome buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he behaving himſelf much contrary to a Miniſter of the Goſpel, in vain words, and unſeemly behaviour: I told him that he being a man that took upon him to be a Teacher of People, <hi>ought not to do ſuch things, but rather reprove them;</hi> upon which he calling me <hi>Quaking Logger-head,</hi> and <hi>Raſcal,</hi> and many ſuch like words, and told me <hi>he would have a Law made to cut off my Ears.</hi> I told him, <hi>I had not done any thing worthy thereof;</hi> and he being filled with Envy, went away Railing, and Raging at me, without a cauſe; after which he promiſed to give me, and ſome other Friends, a meeting, but never did, though I, and my Friends waited ſome time
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172553:4"/>upon it: Afterward he ſent me a Note, wherein he writ, that provided I would come alone, by my ſelf, without any other with me, to <hi>Richard Cluffs</hi> houſe, and alſo to come in ſuch a frame of Spirit, as might induce him to hear me, then he might Diſcourſe with me; and afterwards I carryed a Letter to his houſe, which was written to him by two Friends, but when I came there, he refuſed to ſpeak with me, and alſo to receive the Letter, which I ſent in to him; but he returned it again by his Clerk, who gave it me, and told me that his Maſter would have nothing to do with me, nor yet with my Papers: and ſoon after the ſaid <hi>Manwaring</hi> writ me a Letter, in which was theſe words, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Thomas, <hi>I am ſorry if the Zeal of thy Spirit be to quick for thy Diſcretion, and that a Cudgel muſt beat that out of thee, which the Devil hath blown in.</hi> And ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed his name, <hi>Thomas Manwaring.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo <hi>Francis Smith,</hi> Prieſt of <hi>Thomas Pariſh,</hi> being an aged man, I meeting him upon the Road very drunk, I told him, <hi>It was high time for him to forſake thoſe Works of Darkneſs;</hi> His anſwer was, <hi>that it was high time for me to become a Rogue, and</hi> a <hi>Whelp.</hi> All this with much more, that might be mentioned, have I ſuffered, beſides the Sufferings, which I have born, with the reſt of Friends, by <hi>Cruel Mockings, Scoffings, Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings</hi> and <hi>Cruel Threatnings,</hi> which hath deeply been caſt upon us, both in our houſes, on the high wayes, and other Places, as we have paſſed quietly upon our honeſt occaſions; all which we have born patiently without rendering Evil for Evil: And theſe things have been laid before ſome of you, yet no redreſſe have we had, neither is any amongſt you that have laid theſe our Sufferings to heart, nor at all reproved any of the Evil Doers, for any of theſe things which have been the Cauſe of theſe our Cruel Sufferings, but have rather ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them therein; Notwithſtanding the King ſet forth a <hi>good and wholſome Proclamation,</hi> for the <hi>puniſhment of the Evil Doers,</hi> which thing you put not in Execution, whereby all honeſt ſober People do ſee, that you do not only caſt the <hi>Righteous Law</hi> of <hi>God behind your Backs,</hi> but alſo <hi>the Juſt Act of the King;</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all ye <hi>Rulers, Judges,</hi> and <hi>Juſtices,</hi> and all other <hi>Officers under you</hi> in this <hi>Iſland,</hi> of what ſort ſoever; <hi>Conſider what you
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172553:5"/>have done,</hi> and <hi>what you are doing,</hi> and <hi>lay theſe things to heart,</hi> and <hi>Dread him,</hi> who is a <hi>Dreadfull,</hi> and <hi>Terrible God,</hi> and is <hi>Mighty,</hi> in <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and <hi>Power;</hi> he it is that <hi>Pleadeth our Cauſe</hi> for us, and <hi>taketh notice of all your Actions,</hi> whatſoever <hi>you do,</hi> or ſuffer to be <hi>done againſt us,</hi> be they done never ſo <hi>ſecretly, and will in no wiſe let the guilty go free;</hi> but a <hi>Day</hi> you ſhall know, and aſſuredly will come upon you, that not <hi>one</hi> of you ſhall in any wiſe <hi>eſcape his hand,</hi> in which Day the Holy God, the Righteous Judge of Heaven and Earth, will awake his <hi>Living Witneſs</hi> in every of your <hi>Conſciences;</hi> then you ſhall ſee, and know, that the Lord hath <hi>Regard</hi> to his <hi>People,</hi> whom you have cauſed to <hi>ſuffer</hi> under you by <hi>Cruelty</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> and then will he preſent, to your open views, the <hi>Cryes</hi> and <hi>Groans</hi> of the <hi>oppreſſed,</hi> and all that have <hi>unjuſtly ſuffered under you;</hi> and then ſhall you read before you, as in a Book, <hi>our Sufferings,</hi> and <hi>our Burthens,</hi> which you have <hi>ſo heavily laid upon us;</hi> which we have patiently born in this the day thereof: and theſe things in <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Tenderneſs</hi> have been laid <hi>before you,</hi> that you might not be <hi>Ignorant of them,</hi> which thing hath been <hi>ſlighted by you;</hi> and would not be convinced of the <hi>Evil</hi> thereof; but have rather replyed with <hi>hard ſpeechs,</hi> and <hi>great Threatnings</hi> given forth by ſome of you againſt the <hi>Innocent</hi> and <hi>Beloved of the Lord,</hi> though <hi>deſpiſed of men,</hi> and <hi>forſaken:</hi> and then ſhall all <hi>our Sufferings,</hi> which you have ſuffered to be done againſt us, be <hi>removed from us,</hi> and <hi>we eaſed,</hi> and <hi>you troubled;</hi> and ſo it muſt be, that which hath cauſed <hi>our trouble,</hi> muſt become your <hi>ſhame;</hi> and this will be our Joy, <hi>that we have ſuffered for the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience;</hi> and then that which is <hi>our Joy,</hi> will be <hi>your greateſt Sorrow;</hi> and the more you deſire to be <hi>at eaſe,</hi> the more will your <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row encreaſe:</hi> for verily now is the Lord making <hi>enquiry</hi> among you, and hath conſidered the <hi>Cry</hi> of his <hi>Suffering Seed</hi> through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this <hi>Iſland,</hi> and the <hi>Groans,</hi> and <hi>Sights,</hi> and <hi>Tears</hi> are now <hi>beheld,</hi> and are entered into the Ears of the Lord God of Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, who is ready on the <hi>Seat of Judgement,</hi> and is Mighty in <hi>Majeſty,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> and whoſe Countenance is <hi>Dreadful to the Wicked,</hi> and <hi>Oppreſſors cannot ſtand before him:</hi> Yea veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this I ſay unto you, ye <hi>Bryers,</hi> and <hi>Thorns</hi> (for ſo ye are
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172553:5"/>before him) <hi>he is a conſuming Fire,</hi> who will aſſuredly <hi>burn you up,</hi> except you <hi>ſpeedily Repent,</hi> and <hi>depart</hi> from the <hi>Evil</hi> of <hi>your doings,</hi> elſe <hi>overturned,</hi> and <hi>deſtroyed you ſhall be,</hi> as ſome that are gone before you; for verily, his <hi>Controverſie is againſt you,</hi> and you have <hi>wearied the Lord greatly,</hi> in his <hi>long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> and <hi>forbearing with you,</hi> inaſmuch as he hath given you a Day to <hi>Repent in,</hi> and you <hi>Repented not,</hi> and have ſent his <hi>Servants,</hi> and <hi>Meſſengers from far</hi> to <hi>Declare</hi> amongſt you, and ye <hi>hearkned not;</hi> and hath <hi>tendered his Son unto you,</hi> and ye <hi>received him not;</hi> and though he hath <hi>long cryed</hi> unto you, ye have <hi>not hearkned at all,</hi> neither have ye had <hi>regard unto his Voice,</hi> but have <hi>grieved his Holy Spirit,</hi> and have <hi>ſlighted his Meſſengers,</hi> and done <hi>much wrong</hi> to his <hi>Prophets;</hi> and for theſe things is the <hi>Wrath</hi> of the Lord <hi>kindled againſt you,</hi> and his <hi>ſore Indignation</hi> is <hi>ready</hi> to be <hi>poured forth</hi> upon you: for verily, again I ſay unto you, that the <hi>Crying Sins</hi> that have been <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in this Land</hi> (Oh ye Rulers) are <hi>again</hi> brought into <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance</hi> before the <hi>Lord God Almighty,</hi> and cry <hi>loudly</hi> Day and Night for <hi>Vengeance,</hi> becauſe ye have been <hi>care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</hi> and do <hi>not yet Repent</hi> for theſe things; but are <hi>greedy,</hi> and <hi>eager,</hi> many of you, to <hi>afflict</hi> and <hi>puniſh the Innocent without a Cauſe,</hi> who hath in <hi>Dear Love,</hi> and <hi>Tender Pitty</hi> to your <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Souls warned</hi> you of theſe things, that you might <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> and <hi>turn unto the Lord,</hi> while there is <hi>yet help</hi> for you, whereby you might <hi>eſcape</hi> his <hi>Wrath</hi> that is coming upon you; and for ſo doing have we been accounted by you as <hi>Fools</hi> and <hi>made men;</hi> and thoſe that do <hi>Wickedly,</hi> are accounted <hi>Wiſe</hi> among you, and ſuch do you Honour as your <hi>Counſellors,</hi> but thus ſaith the Lord; <hi>Wo to him that takes Counſel, but not of me,</hi> for what ever that man doth, <hi>his Work ſhall not Proſper;</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye <hi>Rulers,</hi> come forth of your <hi>Worldly Wiſdom,</hi> which is <hi>Fooliſhneſs with God,</hi> by which <hi>Wiſdom</hi> the wiſe Men of the Earth ever took Counſel <hi>againſt the Lord,</hi> and <hi>againſt his People,</hi> to do them hurt, as well in <hi>Ages Paſt,</hi> as <hi>now;</hi> for then by their Wiſdom, they ſet themſelves <hi>againſt Chriſt,</hi> and put him <hi>to Death,</hi> and by their Wiſdom they <hi>Exalted themſelves above him,</hi> and in their Wiſdom, they <hi>withſtood the Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>Baniſhod him out of their Coaſts;</hi> and in their Wiſdom, they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172553:6"/>ſuffered much Violence to be done unto them, by <hi>Cruel Mockings, Scornings, Reviling, Stocking,</hi> and <hi>Impriſoning them;</hi> even as you <hi>have done,</hi> and <hi>ſuffered</hi> to be <hi>done</hi> unto us, this they did, and ſuffered to be done unto the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all their <hi>Learning,</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom.</hi> And thus they went on, and made <hi>great havock</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>People of God</hi> in divers Places, and thoſe things the Apoſtles <hi>laid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them,</hi> being <hi>ſufferers under them,</hi> as we have laid <hi>our ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings before you,</hi> who <hi>have been,</hi> and <hi>yet are</hi> fufferers under you. And thus the <hi>Rulers,</hi> and <hi>People</hi> ran on in their <hi>own Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> in the <hi>Apoſtles times,</hi> crying againſt them, they were a <hi>Dangerous People,</hi> and there were <hi>many</hi> that <hi>followed after them,</hi> and that <hi>Paul</hi> he <hi>turned the World upſide down,</hi> and if they were <hi>ſuffered</hi> to go on, the <hi>Romans would come upon them, and take their Places, and their Nation from them.</hi> This was <hi>their Cry then,</hi> and the ſame is <hi>your Cry now</hi> againſt us; and thus you have raiſed <hi>Falſe</hi> and <hi>Evil</hi> reports <hi>of us,</hi> under a pretence of an <hi>Inſurrection</hi> made in <hi>England,</hi> by a party of <hi>Bloody men,</hi> and have added to it <hi>our Friends,</hi> as though they had had a hand in that <hi>Bloody Plot,</hi> which is a very contrary thing: for Chriſt Jeſus, he came <hi>not to deſtroy mens lives,</hi> but <hi>to ſave them:</hi> and him we take for our Example, Who ſaid, <hi>All that uſe the Sword, ſhall periſh by the Sword,</hi> Mat. 26.52. And this we ſay unto you, that we have <hi>put off our Swords,</hi> and caſt aſide <hi>all Carnal Weapons,</hi> never to make uſe of them more, and the Lord hath given us <hi>Spirituall Weapons,</hi> with <hi>which</hi> we make War, not with the <hi>Perſons</hi> of any men, but with the <hi>Man of Sin,</hi> that dwelleth in them, and with <hi>Spirituall Wickedneſs</hi> that <hi>ſitteth in the high Places,</hi> this alſo was the <hi>Apoſtles Warfare;</hi> and this alſo is <hi>our Warfare,</hi> and our Weapons are <hi>but one,</hi> and we are all of <hi>one mind,</hi> of <hi>one heart,</hi> and <hi>one Spirit,</hi> and we live in <hi>Love one with another,</hi> and deſire to do <hi>good unto all men,</hi> and here we are brought out of the <hi>Strife,</hi> and out of <hi>Contention,</hi> out of <hi>Envy,</hi> and <hi>Malice,</hi> and ſo we are <hi>far</hi> from <hi>Oppreſſion,</hi> and <hi>ſhedding of Blood;</hi> we live out of <hi>Falſhood,</hi> and <hi>Lying, ſpeaking the Truth from our heart,</hi> ſo that we <hi>have no Swearing amongſt us,</hi> nor need of <hi>going to Law;</hi> and herein we do the thing that is <hi>well pleaſing to God,</hi> and we have <hi>no Condemnation</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:172553:6"/>for it: and this is that we labour for, to bring People to, out of the <hi>Evil Doing,</hi> into the <hi>Well doing;</hi> out of <hi>Envy,</hi> and <hi>Strife,</hi> into <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Unitie,</hi> that all may be brought into the <hi>ſame with us,</hi> to live <hi>in Love,</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Quietneſs,</hi> and live in the <hi>Enjoyment of Gods Precious Preſence for Evermore;</hi> and this is that our Souls long for, that it might be well with <hi>every Soul</hi> upon the Earth. Therefore know this, O ye <hi>Rulers,</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> this is the thing the Lord requireth to be done, that ye forthwith ſtand up, and put forth the <hi>Sword of Juſtice</hi> with ſpeed, and let <hi>true Judgement be Executed throughout the Land,</hi> that the <hi>Heathen may fall before you,</hi> that the <hi>Innocent may no longer be puniſhed,</hi> and let the <hi>guilty go free:</hi> Therefore ye Rulers, once more I ſay unto you, <hi>be ye wiſe in this your Day,</hi> which is <hi>far ſpent:</hi> for yet a little while will the Lord <hi>ſpare</hi> you, to <hi>try you,</hi> to ſee whether you <hi>will hearken</hi> hereunto, <hi>or not;</hi> and if ye <hi>reſiſt,</hi> and ſtill go on, in <hi>Rebelling againſt the Lord,</hi> then <hi>ſuddain Deſtruction cometh;</hi> in which Day you will find <hi>no help in the Earth.</hi> And this was upon me from the Lord to lay before you, which I have done in <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs</hi> unto you, and in <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> to my Maker, that whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you will <hi>hear</hi> or <hi>forbear,</hi> I have cleared my Conſcience before the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Who am one that truely deſires the good of you all, that you all may be</hi> partakers of Gods Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Mercy, even as I am, <hi>my Bonds onely excepted, which I wrongfully ſuffer by you, THOMAS CLARK.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Written in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Priſon in <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos,</hi> 
                  <date>11th. 2d. Month. 1661.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:172553:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172553:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
